so how does the internet work most of us
know how to use the internet without
actually understanding how it works sort
of like electricity in your home you use
it every day but may not understand the
mechanics behind it and if the electric
grid is difficult to understand then the
internet must be impossible right wrong
in the next few minutes I'll put you in
the top 10 percent of people who
understand how the internet actually
works for security catalyst comm I'm
Aaron Titus whenever most people think
of the Internet this is what comes to
mind the Internet is not a bubble cloud
even in the new age of cloud computing
the whole fuzzy cloud picture was
created by people more concerned about
job security than education this is the
internet the Internet is a wire actually
buried in the ground it might be fiber
optics copper or occasionally beamed to
satellites or through cell phone
networks but the Internet is simply a
wire the Internet is useful because two
computers connected directly to this
wire can communicate a server is a
special computer connected directly to
the Internet and web pages are files on
that servers hard drive every server has
a unique Internet Protocol address or IP
address just like a postal address IP
addresses help computers find each other
but since seven 2.14 205 done 100 it
doesn't exactly roll off the tongue we
also give them names like google.com
facebook.com or security catalyst comm
so this is how it works
your computer at home is not a server
because it's not connected directly to
the Internet computers you and I use
everyday are called clients because
they're connected indirectly to the
Internet through an Internet service
provider here we'll pretend that this is
my home laptop and I'm using DSL now
let's pretend that I want to visit
aol.com which is coincidentally both a
server and an ISP I hop onto my laptop
with DSL go through my ISP onto the
internet and look at aol.com my computer
connects with AOL comm and I can look at
its web pages now let's say that I want
to send an email to
and Ruth and Ruth has AOL dial-up from
home and I've got a gmail account I log
on to gmail.com and compose a message to
Aunt Ruth's email address Aunt Ruth's at
aol.com
once I click send gmail.com since the
email to Al well calm the next day Aunt
Ruth dials into AOL servers and
retrieves the email whenever an email
picture or webpage travels across the
internet computers break the information
into smaller pieces called packets when
information reaches its destination the
packets are reassembled in their
original order to make a picture email
web page or tweet
okay so imagine you're at work sitting
next to your boss and you're both
surfing online your boss is doing market
research and you're updating your
Facebook profile you're both sending
packets back and forth over the Internet
but what's to keep your packets from
accidentally ending up on your boss's
screen that could be embarrassing the
solution to that problem is IP addresses
and routers everything connected
directly or indirectly to the Internet
has an IP address everything that
includes your computer servers cell
phones and all of the equipment in
between anywhere two or more parts of
the internet intersect there's a piece
of equipment called a router routers
direct your packets around the internet
helping each packet get one step closer
to its destination every time you visit
a website upwards of ten to fifteen
routers may help your packets find their
way to and from your computer imagine
each packet as a piece of candy wrapped
in several layers the first layer is
your computer's IP address your computer
sends the packet to the first router
which adds its own IP address each time
the packet reaches a new router another
layer is added until it reaches the
server then when the server sends back
information
it creates packets with an identical
wrapping as the packet makes its way
over the internet back to your computer
each router unwraps a layer to discover
where to send the packet next until it
reaches your computer and not your
bosses and that's how the internet works
in five minutes or less and you're now
easily in the top 10 percent of people
who understand the basics of the
Internet if you found this video helpful
check out security catalyst comm for all
kinds of ideas on how to protect your
information I'm Aaron Titus