hey guys my name is christian taylor
welcome back to crailer made where i
like to talk about all things
branding marketing and entrepreneurship
when building your first wordpress
website
you probably googled wordpress hosts or
how to install wordpress
and went down the rabbit trail of
exploring the most popular wordpress
hosts
if you're new to wordpress you are
likely confused by the wide variety of
hosting packages offered by companies
what is shared hosting can it run
wordpress
and what is a vps some hosts say they're
managed
some are unmanaged what's the difference
today i'll be breaking down what you
need to know about different types of
web hosting
so first let's start with shared hosting
shared hosting explains itself in the
name
you're sharing your hosting with others
but what does that mean
is this a good thing or a bad thing well
in my video where i explain the basics
of web hosting
i talk about web hosting being a server
or souped up
computer where your website files live
when someone types in your domain name
their computer points to the server
downloads the website files and displays
the website
so with shared web hosting you're
sharing a server with many people
it really varies based on the web host
but there may be as many as
hundreds or thousands of other websites
hosted on the same server as yours
the pros to this are that you can get
hosting at a crazy affordable cost
anywhere from two dollars a month to ten
dollars a month is pretty reasonable for
basic shared hosting it's the most
economic way to start a website and it's
where i recommend you start unless you
know you're going to get a
huge surge in traffic on your website
and that's the downside of shared
hosting
resources your website is on a server
with potentially
thousands of other websites and everyone
is sharing the same ram
and processor it's not always as bad as
it sounds because hosting platforms have
a way to compartmentalize resources and
make sure that there's not a hog website
using up all the power but it's still a
limitation
if you're getting 1 100th of the ram and
processor of a server
your website may load quickly for a
light or medium load
but say you're an ecommerce store and
you get a spike in traffic from a black
friday sale
these types of scenarios are not handled
well by shared hosting
the other downside of shared hosting is
being affected by denial of service
attacks
or other forms of malicious attacks that
can happen on
other users websites i want to be clear
here and say
just because someone else's site on your
server gets hacked
doesn't mean your site is hacked again
shared hosting platforms separate and
compartmentalized hosting accounts to
stop that from happening
but your site can be affected by
specialized forms of attacks like a
denial of service attack
on another website think of it this way
say you're in an office building with a
hundred cubicles
if one cubicle gets breached you're
still safe but if the power to the
entire office building gets compromised
everyone in the office is affected even
if the hacker didn't even know your
website existed
and they were just trying to mess with
someone else's it could cause your site
to go down if they do a certain type of
attack
that affects the server and not just the
website
so is shared hosting really worth it
well again if you're running a casual
blog or small business website
i think shared hosting is absolutely
worth it it's readily available
offered by almost every hosting company
and highly affordable
if you're watching this video and you
just want to build your first wordpress
website
i think you're good to start out with
shared hosting alright so what is vps
hosting a vps is a virtual private
server
now this is a bit of a wacky concept a
vps acts like its own
isolated server but it's shared with
other virtual private servers on
a single physical hardware server you're
probably like
wait a minute so shared hosting is
shared on a server and
a vps is shared too what's the
difference well a vps takes the level of
separation a step further
giving you dedicated resources x amount
of ram
x shares of a cpu and a virtual server
that's your
own oftentimes with cheap shared hosting
companies
oversell their servers this means that
they put more websites on the server
than it can theoretically handle
and they bank on x percentage of
customers never setting up their website
or
setting up a website that never gets any
traffic this usually works out but if
their load is higher than expected
say on black friday everyone's website
suffers
this really comes down to the web host
and with premium hosts like wp engine
and flywheel
you won't face this problem with a vps
while you're still
sharing a physical server you're
guaranteed the resources you're paying
for
it's a virtual computer that requires
its own set of ram
cpu and disk space and no one else can
pull from that
it has to be reserved for you think of
it like this
with shared hosting you have a folder on
a computer with hundreds of other
folders
on the same computer with a virtual
private server
you have a virtual computer all to
yourself so a vps can have any operating
system
windows or linux and you can change any
setting and configure
anything exactly how you want this
effectively beats the two downsides to
shared hosting
you can have significantly more server
resources than with a shared hosting
account
and vpss are known for being easily
scalable
you could go from four gigs of ram to
eight gigs of ram with a click
upgrade storage etc with a quality vps
host
everything is modular and can be
upgraded and downgraded with a snap
so this time on black friday if your
server is unable to handle the load
click a button upgrade to a more
powerful vps for the day
that can handle the surge in traffic and
then when you're done
simply downgrade to the vps you had it's
really cool
furthermore with the vps someone would
have to target your virtual private
server with a hack specifically
even if someone took down another
virtual private server that's on the
same
physical server as yours your server
cannot be affected since it's treated as
an entirely separate computer with
shared hosting there are sometimes a few
different plans you can upgrade to
offering vague promises like double the
speed
but what does that really mean your
server resource customization options
are highly limited with basic shared
hosting
since a vps is your own private server
you get to make the rules for the most
part you can host as many websites as
you like
host email although i don't recommend
that the sky is the limit
with shared hosting there are often
limits to how many sql databases you can
create
or how many domain names you can connect
to one hosting account
but with the vps it's all yours and you
can do whatever you want with it
of course it's your job to find a vps
with the appropriate power for your
needs
and if you're going to put a large
amount of websites on it you'll want to
pay for a beefier vps that can handle
the load
so a vps is indefinitely more powerful
but it does come with big downsides
a vps on its own is a massive headache
to manage if you aren't a tech geek
i consider myself tech savvy but it's a
challenge for me to manage a traditional
vps by itself
i say traditional vps by itself because
this is where the concept of
managed hosting comes in a managed vps
host like cloudways will allow you to
have your own vps from a cloud provider
you choose
but they handle all the technical side
of getting it set up and configuring it
you have a clean and simple management
panel so you can just add a new website
to the server whenever you want
typically with a vps you'd have to get
your hands dirty and mess with a command
line
but with a managed vps you just have a
convenient panel like
shared hosting but you get to leverage
the big power advantages of a vps
obviously this is a lot more expensive
than an unmanaged vps but it can
definitely be worth it depending on your
needs
so the last main kind of hosting is
dedicated hosting or a dedicated server
and this one's pretty easy to understand
take all the advantages of a vps
but now visualize yourself having an
entire physical server to yourself
picture a server in your head got it you
see it
yeah that's yours all of it the entire
thing
it's only your stuff hosted on it and
nothing else
in my honest opinion a dedicated server
is in some ways
worse than a vps sure it's theoretically
the most powerful option because you're
not sharing it with anyone
but you can't easily upgrade it or
downgrade it like a vps
it's also insanely expensive and i
personally would stay away from a
dedicated server
unless you already knew what it was
before watching this video
there's really no reason to use it
unless you're a giant company and you
need multiple dedicated servers working
together to host your files
but then again if you know what a
dedicated server is you probably know
what aws
azure and digitalocean are too and
modular cloud computing is looking like
a far
better choice for very advanced hosting
projects instead of dedicated servers
alright so that was a lot to process but
i want to give some examples of
real-world hosting packages and
categorize where they fall to help you
better understand different types of web
hosting
let's look at dreamhost here we can see
that they actually offer
every kind of hosting we talked about
we've got standard shared hosting which
is affordable
comes with basic support and a
management panel we have managed vps
hosting
managed wordpress hosting and dedicated
server hosting
now wait a minute what is managed
wordpress hosting is it shared
is it a vps well in this case it's
shared
but it's premium managed wordpress
hosting think
dreampress wp engine flywheel and kinsta
these hosts go above and beyond to
provide a reliable and fast
experience using isolated containers
similar to a vps
in other words with a premium managed
wordpress host
it is shared but you're not going to
face the major throttling problems
or other issues you get with economy
shared hosting
since it's managed you can expect great
support access to staging environments
and
automatic backups with one-click restore
if money is no factor for you this is
arguably the best wordpress hosting you
can get for your site when it comes to
the different types of web hosting
i think you need to step back and look
at the features and practicality
first over the category is the hosting
within your budget do you require
hands-on support or are you
okay with poking around and figuring
things out do you need development tools
like a staging environment and automatic
daily backups
focus on these first and the features
will help you narrow down whether you
need shared hosting
vps hosting and managed or unmanaged
hosting
if you'd like to see me create a video
talking about what to look for in a web
host
drop a comment below if you're starting
out i'd recommend basic shared hosting
from namecheap or dreamhost
if you need more power or features like
a staging environment or high-end
support
go with flywheel or wp engine if you
just have one website
if you host several wordpress websites
and are looking for the ultimate managed
vps host where you can host as many
websites as you'd like
i recommend trying cloudways i
personally use wp engine
and cloudways i have my highest traffic
website hosted on wp engine
and i have a two gigabyte digitalocean
server with cloudways that hosts the
rest of my websites
including all of my trailer media sites
so what type of hosting do you use
i'd love to know your thoughts in the
comments down below and if you like this
video do be sure to hit that subscribe
button and click the bell so you don't
miss when i release new videos
with that said i will catch you guys
next time