hi i'm tony messer from picaweb and in
this video
i'm going to explain everything you need
to know about web hosting
at the end of this video you'll have all
the information you need to make an
informed decision
when you buy a hosting service sound
like a plan
great let's get started
[Music]
okay so the basics hosting is the home
of your website
if you're on a website you'll need
somewhere to host it that's exactly
what web hosting is now there are
different types of
hosting service you've got shared
hosting reseller hosting
virtual private servers or vps and
dedicated servers
but we're going to be looking at shared
hosting in this video because that's the
most popular
and affordable type of hosting so
hosting is basically
the computer and network infrastructure
that keeps your website available
across the internet it also provides
other key services like email for you
so how does it all work well it all
starts with a server which is basically
a powerful
computer which is stored in a highly
secure
purpose-built multi-million pound
facility called a data center
the data center provides the network and
power connectivity
with temperature control backup systems
fire suppression and high levels of
physical security
security is also important at the server
level so the servers are actually built
with dual components for critical
components
things like hard drives and power supply
units
and the reason for this is to make sure
that your website is available
at all times so when you order a hosting
service
what you're actually purchasing is the
physical disk space on the server
as well as the bandwidth which is the
network connection
for the server and you'll often see
hosting advertised in terms of disk
space and bandwidth so you might see for
example
five gig five gigabytes of disk space
and 100 gigabytes
of bandwidth per month so the disk space
that covers
your website and all of your files
including key files things like your
emails
and the monthly bandwidth allowance this
is the amount of traffic that comes in
and out of your website and your hosting
space so that will usually most of it
will be made up by email
traffic in and out but also things like
people visiting your website and when
you actually publish
your website files in order to manage
your web hosting
you'll need access to a user-friendly
interface called a control panel
the one of the most popular control
panels is called cpanel
and this allows you to manage key areas
of your hosting things like setting up
email addresses
managing domains and forwarding managing
databases
that kind of thing and this shields you
basically from any of the sort of
technical
aspects of the hosting if you want to
build your own website
you can use a tool like website builder
which is included
and this basically allows non-technical
users
to build and maintain a website and it
uses templates pre-made templates so you
just add your own
text and images and then can publish it
for more advanced users or maybe you've
got a web designer
then there are more advanced tools and
applications which are included
for free so so you can sort of manage
databases and also use
other tools to build your website and
these kind of tools these applications
these include popular content management
systems like wordpress
as well as more advanced e-commerce
tools like
prestashop and magento so you can start
selling online
other security features are things like
anti-spam software
and data backup and these ensure the
integrity of your email
and your data if if you're with one
hosting company and you want to transfer
to another hosting company that's very
straightforward this is a process
called migration and basically your
files are copied from your current
hosting to your new hosting service
there are just a couple of
small changes that need to be made to
your domains and name server settings
for that process to be fully completed
okay so there you have it that's your
quick guide
to web hosting i hope you found that
useful if you like this video
don't forget to give it the big thumbs
up and subscribe to our channel
so you can get updated whenever we have
any new content for you
also please feel free to share it with
your friends and also
anyone who you know who's got who's
looking for a hosting service
if you've got any comments just put them
below i would really appreciate it
i do read them and i will get back to
you okay thanks very much for your time
then
bye-bye