[Music]
this video is sponsored by dev mountain
if you're interested in learning web
development
ios or ux design devmountain is a
12-week design and development bootcamp
intended to get you a full-time position
in the industry
to learn more visit devmountain.com or
click the link in the description below
hey what's going on guys so in this
video i want to talk about something
that i think isn't talked about often
enough and that's the http protocol
that we as web developers work with
every day and
whether you're a backend full stack or
even front-end developer it's important
to understand http
and the whole request response cycle so
in this video we're going to touch on
how all this works we'll look at the
different types of responses
methods status codes and you know what
you get back from a server
when you send a request and we're going
to go through some slides
and i'd like to test some of this stuff
out with node.js and express
along with postman which is an http
client
and i think express is a great framework
to kind of give you
some examples of how http works because
we handle everything ourselves it's very
minimalistic
we handle the request the response
directly rather than
having it be abstracted like it is in
many higher level frameworks
so even if you're not familiar with
express or node that's fine we're not
focusing on the specific framework or
language
so let's first talk about what http is
it stands for
hypertext transfer protocol and it's
basically responsible for communication
between web servers and clients it's the
protocol of the web
so every time you open up your browser
and you visit a web page or you submit a
form
or you click a button that sends some
kind of ajax request or fetch request
something like that
you're you're using http and you're
going through what's called the request
and response cycle you make a request
and you get a response back
that has something called headers and
something called the body
and we're going to look more into that
cycle in a bit all right so it's
important to understand that http is
stateless meaning that every request is
completely independent
okay when you make one request visiting
a web page or you go to another page
after that or reload the page
it doesn't remember anything about the
previous
basically transaction you can kind of
look at each request as a single
transaction
now there's other things we can utilize
to for instance hold login data
and make a more enhanced user experience
things like
programming local storage cookies
sessions stuff like that
but just know that http at its core is
completely stateless
so what is https and i'm sure that a lot
of you guys know this stuff but just for
people that don't https stands for
hypertext transfer protocol secure
and it's basically where all the data
that's sent
back and forth is encrypted by something
called ssl which stands for secure
sockets layer or by tls which is the
transport security layer so anytime you
have users that are sending sensitive
information
you should always it should always be
over https especially if it's like
credit card data social security numbers
you want to have a high level of
security for that stuff
and even things like contact forms you
should have https
a lot of websites and applications now
are just forcing https
on every page which isn't a bad idea and
you can do this by installing
an ssl certificate on your web host and
there's
there's different levels of security
different levels of certificates as well
all right so when a request is made to a
server it has some kind of method
attached to it
and there's there's more than this these
are the main four that you're going to
be working with
um and these are the ones i'm going to
go over but just know there are there
are a couple more
so a get request is used when you want
to get or fetch data from its
from the server this could be just
loading a standard html page
loading assets like css or images json
data xml data
and so on so every time you visit a web
page you're making a get request to the
server via http
now a post request is usually used when
you're posting data when you're adding
something to the server adding a
resource
typically when you submit a form like
let's say a contact form
you'll be making a post request if
you're submitting
uh maybe a blog post you're creating a
new blog post that's going to be a post
request
you're sending data to the server and
typically that data will be stored in a
database somewhere
you can also have forms that make get
requests but it's less secure because
the stuff that you send in the form is
actually going to be visible in the url
so typically you don't want to use a get
request with a form unless it's some
kind of search form where all you're
doing is filtering data
that's coming back from the server
you're not actually posting anything
all right and then we have a put request
which is used to update data that's
already on the server so if you have a
blog post you want to edit it
maybe change the image or change some
text typically you would do that with a
put request
and then a delete request of course just
deletes data from the server
all right so with each request and
response
using http you have something called a
header you have something called the
body
so the body typically with a response is
going to be
the html page that you're you're trying
to load the the json data whatever is
being sent from the server
and then when you make a request you can
also send a request body
for instance when you submit a form the
form fields you're submitting
are part of the request body all right
now when it comes to the header
you also have request headers and
response headers in in something called
a general header
okay so it's basically divided into
three parts and there's different fields
on each part so
typically a header will look something
like this you'll make a
method like a get request to a path or
url
with a protocol in this case http 1.1
and then you'll have all these different
header fields and a lot of these
you're not really going to need to care
about but it's good to know
what some of the more common ones do and
what they are especially
with the general uh part of it so in
general we have the request url which is
pretty straightforward it's just the url
you're requesting
the request method so if it's a get
request post request and so on
the status code this is probably the
most important and i'm going to go over
status codes in the next slide
the remote address which is the ip of
the remote computer
the refer policy so if you're if you go
to a page from another page it might
have some information on that
uh and whatever the poll referrer policy
is i'm not that familiar with it
um the response header fields you have
server
so if it's apache or nginx or something
like that
and a lot of times this will be hidden
just to prevent hackers from knowing
what type of server the the website uses
so set cookie is used for servers to
send small pieces of data called cookies
from the server to the client and then
content type so every response has a
content type
for instance if it's an html page it'll
have
a content type of text html
css files would be text css
images you have image slash png image
slash jpeg
if it's json data it'll be application
slash json
this is something that i think is really
important to know with the different
content types
and then you also have the content
length which is just that it's the
length
it's in octets which are i believe 8-bit
bytes
and then also the date okay and there's
other fields as well but
i'm not going to list every single one
or every possible one
so some common request fields are
cookies now
if you have a cookie that was previously
sent by the server and you need to send
it
back to the server you would do it in
this field
you also have a bunch of accept fields
like accepting coding
except character set except language
these are just the different encodings
and languages and stuff that
um uh the client is able to understand
okay content type again so if you're
sending data
like let's say you're sending json you'd
want to set this to application
slash json and then you also have
content length
as well so authorization um
remember http is stateless so you might
need to send some type of token
within the header the authorization and
the header so that you can for instance
validate a user to
access a protected route or a protected
page
unless you're using something like
sessions on the server
and then the user agent is typically a
long string that has to do with the
software that the user is
is using so the operating system the
browser things like that
and then the refer has info regarding
the
referring site if you were to to click
on a link or whatever
so these are just some of the the more
common
header fields but there are more so if
you want to check out the http spec you
can look more into that
all right so http status codes are
really important to understand at least
the the most common ones
so basically you have ranges you have
the 100 through 500 range
so 100 is informational basically this
is
uh it means the request has been
received and the process is continuing
it's processing
200 means that it was successful
so successfully received understood and
accepted
the 300 range usually has to do with
redirection
or further action must be taken 400
range is a client error meaning that the
request doesn't have what it needs from
the client
so let's say the server needs a name
field
sent in the in the request body and you
don't send that you're going to get a
400 error
or somewhere in that range and then 500
is usually a server error okay so the
server failed to fulfill
an apparent valid request so everything
seems okay as far as what you send to
the server but you still get an error
something's wrong on the server side
all right now these are some important
status codes i should say common status
codes that you should remember
so 200 is just okay it means everything
is is fine you make the request
you get the html page you get a 200
response
201 is okay but it means something was
created so if you're
creating a blog post and everything goes
okay then you might get a 200
201 response 301 is
usually moved to a new url so this has
to do with redirection
304 is typically not modified meaning
that
if you visit a page and it and it gets
cached and it hasn't changed at all
then you'll have a 304 response
or status 400 again bad requests so if
you're not sending the correct data
to the server 401 is typically or is
unauthorized so if you are missing a
token or something like that
you're not authorized you might get a
401 404 we all know what that means it's
not
found if you're looking for some page on
the server that doesn't exist
or some resource that doesn't exist
you're going to get a 404
and then 500 is just an internal server
error this could mean pretty much
anything on the server side
all right so those are the status codes
those are really important to
really memorize and understand so the
last thing i want to quickly
mention is that there is http version
two we've been dealing with 1.1 for a
long long time
now all the changes to version 2 are
pretty much under the hood meaning you
don't have to go and change the way your
applications work
all the status codes everything like
that is all the same
it's just faster and more efficient okay
so it does stuff like
reduces latency by enabling full request
and response multiplexing
so it's faster it's more efficient it's
more secure
and this is just a simple image to kind
of of show you
um uh that it can you can use
multiplexing so for instance
we get our html page get a response get
our style sheet
get our response get our script get our
response so this is 1.1
with http 2 multiplexing we can get our
html and then get
all of our scripts and style sheets
basically in one shot here and send the
responses at the same time
now i'm not extremely familiar with hdb2
i haven't read the spec i haven't worked
with it that much
but just know it is available it is out
there so you might want to look more
into it
all right so now we're going to jump
into express so i can give you some
examples
on dealing with a request body and
headers and sending status codes and
stuff like that
all right guys so we're going to jump
into our little express server in a
second but i just want to first show you
an example
on an actual website i'm just going to
use my twitter profile but you can go to
any website you want
and go to your dev tools in my case my
chrome dev tools
and then click on the network tab and if
i go ahead and reload the page here
it's going to make all the requests it
needs it's going to get all the files
from the server
and it's going to show them down here so
you can see the different types
the status of 200 which means they
everything's okay
the size this is the document the main
html document and then we have all of
our javascript files
our style sheets our images xhr which is
any ajax requests that were made
but let's take a look at the main
document here and
under response you're going to see the
body which is of course the html file
okay same thing with preview now headers
is where you can actually see all the
different header fields and remember
in the slides i showed you that there's
three different sections
general response and request so if we
look at general you can see our request
url
which is just the entire url the request
method is get we made a get request
status code is 200 so everything's okay
we get a little green dot
the remote address and refer policy now
if we look in response we have things
like cache control there's a bunch of
stuff here that
i'm not going to explain some of the
stuff i don't even understand
but we have like the content length
their security policy
and then down here we should have like
the content type
which is text html the character set is
utf-8
the date um what else here we have
set cookie so they set some cookies on
the client
status 200 down here we have like
response time stuff like that
and then in the request headers we have
the authority which is the
the root domain we have it's a get
request
the path is my profile https is the
scheme
and then down here at the very bottom we
have the user agent which is this long
string which describes my environment
so it has it tells you i'm on a mac
intel based
os x um it's kind of confusing because
it says mozilla it says safari and
chrome
i'm actually on chrome so it shows my
the version of chrome that i'm on
all right so that's the user agent so i
just want you to take note of these
values
after what we went through in the slides
and if you want to narrow
it down by files we can see like all the
css that was loaded
so if i click on one of these i can see
all the info for that file including the
content type which is text css if i want
to look at the ajax requests here
so like this one right here this should
be application slash
jason and if we look at the response
this is what it got us so the number of
results
some i guess some user information so
these are all the different
uh xhr or ajax requests that were made
all right so when you use the fetch api
or axios or old school ajax this is
where it's going to show up so just get
familiar with the network tab it's
it's it can be a little daunting at
first but
it's it's really helpful it lets you
know what's going on it shows you the
load times and all that stuff
all right so enough with that let's jump
into
i'm going to show you postman first and
if you don't have this
client which is just awesome especially
if you're building apis
you can get it at getpostman.com and as
you can see i can make any type of
request
so get post put patch delete all these
other ones to any url
in fact i'll go ahead and make a request
to
twitter.com traversingmedia
slash okay and i'm going to make sure
it's a get request just like the browser
made
and i'm going to get the same exact
thing i'm going to get all the html it
doesn't render it
um well actually can we preview it i've
never actually tried to preview
html is disabled would you like to
proceed legacy
yeah so whatever you get the html
and then headers will give you all the
response headers
so we can see the content type that
we're getting
set cookie status all that stuff if we
want to look at the cookies we have that
tab as well
it shows us the status up here as well
with the load time and the size
okay so we can make any requests from
here that we can
make in the browser and more because we
can actually do put and delete and all
that stuff
so this is a fantastic tool for testing
apis
that you're building so let's jump into
express
real quick i just have a basic express
server running here
on localhost 5000 and
don't worry about it if you're not
familiar with express basically all
we're doing here is
bringing it in initializing it setting
it to listen on port 5000 and we have
one
endpoint meaning that if we make a get
request
so we said app.get to slash which is the
index page
it's going to run this function that has
access to this request and response
object
and with our response object we can call
dot send
which will just send basically just
whatever we put in here
to the the client okay in this case just
a string of hello from express
so if i go to postman and i make a get
request to http
localhost port 5000 i get hello from
express
and i could do the same thing in the
browser
get hello from express all right if i
open my network tab and reload
oh i'm going to go to all here and you
can see that i get a 304
which means not modified because it was
cached and it didn't change
so it gave me this 304. if i were to
change this like say hello from express1
and save and go and reload
now i get a 200 if i reload again i get
a 304 because it didn't change
but over here i can see all my headers
so same stuff that i saw with twitter
there's just a lot less
because there's a lot less going on
alright so in postman same thing i can
see all my headers
now with postman i can send all kinds of
stuff i can send
a request body i can send headers so we
have a lot more freedom to
to to basically interact with the
request and response cycle
now in express actually one thing i want
to show you
is the content type which by default if
you use res.send and you just send a
string it's going to be
html okay in fact i could
put i don't want to make this too much
about express but i could put
html right in here and if i go to my
browser you can see that that actually
renders
all right now if i were to put jason in
here
let's get rid of this and let's say
msg we'll just say message hello and i
save that
and we go back to postman and send you
can see the content type has changed so
with express res.send will basically
detect to the content type
as best as it can okay but there is
a res.json which is what you should use
if you're sending json so if i do that
it'll give me the same thing all right
it shows the json in the body
now we can also get our header
values or header fields if we want so
i'm just going to do a res.send just to
kind of show you the output of this but
if i take my request
object i can do dot header
and then in parentheses any header value
i want like let's say the host
so i save that and i go back to postman
and send i get a response with my host
localhost 5000. okay if i wanted let's
say the user agent
we'll do user das dash agent
and if we go back and send we get in
this case
postman runtime because i'm using
postman as a client so this is going to
be different than what we saw in chrome
if i go back to chrome and reload we're
going to see this
okay which is different because we're
using a different utility a different
client
all right so just wanted to show you we
could do that
we can also get just the raw headers so
basically all of them if we do request
dot raw headers
and if we go back to postman and send
you can see we basically get an array
with all the headers the cache control
postman token since we're using postman
the user agent
the accept value the host all that stuff
okay and we can send headers as well
which i'll show you in a little bit
so we can get header values um what else
do i want to show you
so let's actually
let's change this to a different row
let's do like
slash contact we'll say that this is a
contact form
and what i want to show you now is how
we can send data
to the server in the request body when
we send a request we can attach
data to that to the body and the way
that we access that i'll just go ahead
and send it so we can
view it the way that we access that is
with that request
object has body so re request dot body
now this won't work for for adjacent
data unless you put this piece of
middleware in
and it won't work for form data unless
you put this in that's just an express
thing
all right but let's go ahead and save
that
excuse me and let's make a request here
to
actually i want to i'm sorry i want to
change it to a post request
okay if you're sending data you want it
to be a post so we simply change
get to post here so i'm going to save
that and go back
and then make a post request to slash
contact now if i just send it as is i
get an empty object because request.body
is
empty however if i want to send any data
i can click on the body tab and
typically you would do this in your
front end like in your javascript
whether it's react
or angular or whatever but this is just
for
basically testing apis
so from here i could send form data if i
want now notice when i click this
www form url encoded
it automatically puts a content type in
my header
okay because you need to send this along
too so we're actually sending a header
value here
and then in the body i could put a key
like let's say name
so this is just simulating a form on a
website
so we'll say value brad
and let's do email and
brad at gmail okay so if i go ahead and
send that we're going to see that down
here because
we sent that we sent the request.body
if i do just request.body.name
and i send that we just get brad
all right and you see how i sent the
content type in the header if i want to
access that
i can do request.header
and i can grab the content dash
type and
let's go back and send and we get this
url encoded that's the type
all right we can also send raw json so
if i go ahead and
get rid of that header and put in
a different content type we actually get
a little drop down here
so content type i'm going to set it to
application slash json
go to body and instead of this url
encoded i'm going to choose
raw okay because we can send raw jason
so name
and we'll say john doe
and i'll go ahead and send and i get
application json because that's the
content type
but again i could access the body if i
want so if i want to get rid of that and
just do
request dot body and save
and send that we get our json of john
doe
all right if we look at the headers
content type
okay so hopefully this is kind of making
sense to you guys that
that don't have a lot of experience with
this type of thing
now what about statuses in postman if i
make a post request to contact one
and i send that you can see that i get a
status of 404. you guys all know what
that means it's not found
and it just gives me this cannot post
contact one
so we can send our own statuses i mean
when we do a successful res.send or
res.json
it's automatically 200 but we can have
conditionals
and create different statuses based on
that
so let's say that this route we actually
need to have a name if there's no name
we want to send back
a 400 response which means it's a bad
request
so i'll simply do an if statement here
and let's say if not request dot
body dot name
then let's go ahead and do a res i'm
sorry we want to return
a res dot status okay so this is how we
can send a status code and i'm going to
send a 400
and then after that we could do dot json
or
dot send i'm going to do dot send and
i'm just going to say
name is required
all right now i'm going to go under the
if statement if a name is included then
and typically you would do like some
database stuff
here you would put the the contact into
the database or whatever
but i'm going to do a res and i'm going
to do another
status here of 201 which means that
everything's okay and something was
created
okay it means created and i'll do a dot
send
and then let's just do i'll put a
template
string in here and say thank you
and then we can actually put in the
request dot
body dot name all right so let's save
that let's go back to postman
and let's get rid of the name here let's
not send it
and we get name is required okay because
it's looking for that in the body
in the request body so if i send it
actually i'll just
undo that so if i say name john
and i send now we get thank you john
because it passes we're sending that
that request.body.name
okay let's see so the next thing
i want to look at is header values now
a lot of times when you're dealing with
full stack applications you
use tokens or json web tokens for um
for authentication and you send that and
you can either send it in the
authorization
i like to send it in x off token
in a value called x auth token so what
i'll do here is create another route
let's do app dot we'll do post
to let's say slash login
all right and then what i want to do
here is check for a token
in the header so i'm going to say if
there's no and then the way that we
access header values i already showed
you this we can do request
dot header
and then i'm going to check for x dash
off
dash token okay so if that's not there
then let's send
let's send an error let's do return and
one thing i want to mention is notice i
did the return
status here and not here it's because
you don't need it if it's the
only or the last one but if you have it
before if you have another response here
even if it's within an if statement that
doesn't pass
you're going to get an error that says
headers already sent so make sure you
use return up here
okay so i'm just going to return
res.status
and let's say if no token
is included in the header then we'll
send to 400
and we'll just send an error that says
no token
okay now let's do a pretend validation
for the token so
i'll go ahead and just say if the
request.header
x dash auth
dash token let's say if that
is not equal to the string of 1 2
3 4 5 6 then it's going to be invalid so
i'm going to return
a response status of 401 which is
unauthorized so i'll do send
and we'll just say not
authorized okay and then down here if
everything passes we'll do a res.send
and we'll say logged in
so we're just kind of simulating a login
process
obviously it would be much more in depth
we'd need to use actual token
json web tokens and validate them and so
on but let's save that let's try this
out so if we go
back to postman make a post request to
slash
login and we don't need any body data
because we're just dealing
with headers and we can clear out
content type let's just send that
so we get no token now i'm going to add
a header value of
x dash auth dash token
but i'm going to do 1 2 three four five
which is wrong
so we get not authorized if i do one
through six
we get logged in okay so just an example
of of how you can authenticate through
um tokens in the in the headers
okay and by the way if you're interested
in we do this in my mern stat course we
do all this
this type of stuff all right so
let's do uh let's simulate a put request
so i'm just going to get rid of this
so for put requests we would do app.put
and maybe it's like a blog post so we'd
have like slash
posts now usually you'd have to identify
which post you're updating
and you would do that within the url so
it would be like
colon id which is like a placeholder
all right and i know that we're doing a
lot of express
stuff but my goal here is to just get
you familiar with
sending request body fields header
fields dealing with that
sending status codes back so
here usually what would happen is we
would do some database stuff
so database stuff to update the
the post and then send back a response
let's do a res.json
and we'll send the id now if you want to
get the id that's passed in you can
actually use request
dot params and then whatever the param
in this case id
and then the title we're going to send
in the body so i'll do request
dot body dot title
okay so request params is going to
access the url values
request body will access the form data
or the json data that you send in the
body
so we'll save that and from postman we
can make a put request
to slash and we'll do
post slash 99
okay so this will get accessed with
request.params and then
in the body since we're going to be
sending data we actually have to add a
header value of content type
and i'm just going to send raw json so
we'll do
application jason and then let's send
the title
so title my blog post
and if we send we get a response back
with the id of 99 because that's what we
put in here and then
the title that's what we put in the body
and i could put anything
at all in here okay so hopefully that
just
gives you a good an idea of how put
requests work
but typically you would do an update of
the database using that id
and then delete would would basically be
the same thing
so we just do app.delete and
include the id delete it in the database
and then return
maybe most likely not going to return
the post because it's deleted so you
might do something like a message
a message and say post
actually what we could do is we could
say
post and then take the id
and say deleted okay so now from postman
we could make a delete request
we don't need any of this we don't need
this and the headers
we could just send that we get post that
deleted
all right so yeah i mean hopefully this
helps a little bit
understand how this goes now with
express we can set
a static folder and this pertains to if
you just have a static html website
where you have a bunch of css files and
you know javascript files and stuff like
that so
in express what we can do is we can
actually
set a specific folder to be our static
folder
and we do that with app dot use
and in here i can just say
express dot static
and then here i can put the location of
the folder which is going to just be
public
so now in my folder structure actually i
already have a public folder i forgot i
created that
with an index html file that just says
hello world
so i should be able even though i don't
have a route
for my index page i have this static
folder so that should load the html file
if i go to my browser we can see it
there and if i go to postman
we can see oops we want to make get
to the index and now we can see the
hello world
if i wanted to create like some css
files in my public folder
i could do css and
create style.css and we'll just do like
body
we'll say background sky blue
so i'll save that let's create a
javascript in our public folder as well
we'll say
folder js and file
main.js and i'll just do uh
console log of one two three
i just wanna include these files in my
my html so back in my html i'll do a
link
to css slash style and then i'll
link my javascript down here oops
script source and
js slash main js all right so i just
want to show you that if i go to chrome
now
and i reload in my network tab i'm going
to see
all those files okay they're all getting
loaded we have our main document here
which has the content type of text html
we have our style sheet
okay text style we have our javascript
so we can see all that stuff we can also
see
the body of each one as well
okay and it would be the same if you had
like some kind of shared host and you
just uploaded your html and css and all
that you get the same
type of thing here and of course we can
narrow the files down
css javascript and if i had some kind of
fetch fetch request or ajax request that
would show
under xhr okay so
hopefully this you know this gives you a
good idea of how
http works i know that we focused a lot
on express but again i think it's a good
example just because
you have direct access to everything to
all the headers and
body on both sides so now keep in mind
when you deploy
a node.js and express app you're you're
not going to serve it like this from
port 5000 you're going to use something
like nginx
use like a reverse proxy and there's a
whole bunch of configuration that goes
into it
but as far as how http works it's
it's the same way the same uh you send
data receive data in the same way
all right so thanks a lot guys thanks
for watching if you like this please
leave a like and i'll see you next time