what's up Internet today I'm gonna be
explaining what is a domain name and a
little bit about how a domain name works
you're probably here because you're
looking to start a website or maybe
you're just sick of watching videos of
kids yodeling in Walmart and you want to
learn something new either way my name
is Dale and welcome to create a
pro-western so in the simplest terms a
domain name is just the address to your
website so think of the Internet as a
vast map full of avenues and streets and
turns everywhere and think of your
website as your house in order for
anyone to find their way to your house
even you you'll need an address this
address is your domain name every
website has an IP and an IP is just a
seemingly random string of numbers so
when you register and purchase a domain
name it's almost like saving your home
address as home into your phone
it gives that IP address a simple easy
to remember name that anyone can type in
and get to your website this is because
it would be really difficult to remember
a random string of numbers every time
you want to go to apple.com
or night B or whatever it may be let's
say create a pro website com you can
remember that it's simple
rather than 6 6 . 1 3 4 . 2 9 9 I made
that up like how are you supposed to buy
an Apple watch with that so let's say
that you type in create a pro website
com whenever you hit enter your computer
sends a request to a bunch of servers
that make up the DNS and DNS just stands
for domain name system this domain name
system looks up the correct IP address
and just points your computer into the
right direction all within less than a
millisecond wow the Internet is a
magical place so that's what a domain
name is and a little bit about how it
works so if you'd like to purchase a
domain name
because you're gonna say start a new
website for your new business or a
portfolio or a blog or whatever it might
be I will put a link in the description
below this video where you can do
exactly that for very cheap so check it
out and before you go every new
subscriber and liked that I get on this
video helps my tiny humble channel grow
so it would just be immense to me if you
would smash that subscribe button and
give me a thumbs up if you found this
helpful
alright guys see you on the next video
[Music]