hey everyone this is kamran and today
we're going to talk about the dns
or the domain name system dns is one of
those topics that anyone who develops
for the web
should know about it is a broad topic so
i'm going to divide this lesson into two
videos
in this lesson we're going to talk about
what is dns and how does it work
and the next one is going to be about
the dns records and how to debug the
issues with the help of dig
traced out and nslookup so what is dns
before we learn about the dns we need to
know what is internet
and before we learn about the internet
we need to know what is a network
network is just a group of computers and
other devices that are connected to each
other so for example if at your home you
have a printer you have a laptop and a
desktop
and all of these are connected to each
other these are all forming a network
moving on we have internet which is a
global network of networks
so for example if you at your home have
a home network and then your friend has
a home network of his own
and then he has another friend which has
a home network and all these networks
are grouped together to form a bigger
network
so internet is similar to that just a
global network of all the networks
now on the internet if you have to
communicate with some other device you
need to know how to find it
to find the device on the internet we
use something called the ip address
so each device on the internet has an ip
address which has a numeric
format and it looks like this and it is
used to locate that device on the
internet
and same goes for the websites that you
visit on the internet
the ip address of the server where that
website is hosted
is used to load the website in the
browser but how does it work because we
normally put the domain name in the
browser
how is the browser able to find the ip
address of the server
the answer to that is the browser uses
something called a dns
which helps us get the ip address from
the domain name so
the browser sends the dns the domain
name
and it gets back the ip address and once
it has the ip address it can go on the
network
and hop from different routers till it
reaches the
server and then it loads the website
from there
okay now that we've got the high level
understanding of the internet
and how it works let's look at the dns
and see how it works internally
so first of all we have the browser so
the user enters the website in the
browser
and tries to open it as we know that the
first step is dns resolution so the
browser needs to find the ip address
of the website first of all the browser
will look at the cache
and see if it has the ip address of the
website from any previous visits if it
doesn't find it there then it will look
at the dns cache and see if we have the
ip address there and if it is also not
there then it will look at the host file
to see if we have a mapping from the
domain name to the ip address
defined there if it is able to find the
ip address in any of these places
it will load the website from there and
it will not do any of the next steps
that we will mention now if it is not
able to find the ip address in any of
these caches
or the host file the next step is the
recursive dns servers this is normally
your isp
or internet services provider which
provides you the internet now it doesn't
know anything about the
domain name but it has the caches from
any previous visits
so it is possible that some other user
might have visited the same website
and might have the cached ip address if
it is able to find the cache type
address it will just return the ip
address from here and it does not have
to go to the next step
and if the ip address is not found here
then the next step is the root dns
servers
now root dns servers also do not have
the ip address information for the
domain name
but they have the information about the
tld or the top level domain
so for example if you're looking for
google.com so the tld
or the top level domain is dot com so it
knows
who might have the information about all
the dot com domains so it will just
return the information about the
tld server now the tld server also
doesn't know where the domain
is but it knows the final place where
might
the domain information be which is the
authoritative name server
so it will just return the information
about the authoritative name server and
the request will go to the authoritative
name server
get the ip address of the domain name
from there
the ip address will then come to the
recursive dns servers
where it might be cached and then it
will be sent to the user's computer
and then to the browser and then the
browser will request the website
servers and get the website from there
and this is how the
ip address of the website is found on
the internet with the help of dns
and that's it for our lesson i hope you
enjoyed it if you have any questions or
comments
leave them below and i will see you in
the next lesson